<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A godlie and fruitefull sermon, made vpon the 20. &amp; 21. verses of the 14. chapter of the booke of Genesis wherein there is taught, what prouision ought to be made for the mynister. Very necessary to be learned of all Christians. By Eusebius Paget.</title>
            <title>Godlie and fruitefull sermon, made upon the 20. &amp; 21. verses of the 14. chapter of the booke of Genesis.</title>
            <author>Pagit, Eusebius, 1547?-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1583</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08816</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19102</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105803</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841529</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841529</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6118</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08816)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6118)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1324:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A godlie and fruitefull sermon, made vpon the 20. &amp; 21. verses of the 14. chapter of the booke of Genesis wherein there is taught, what prouision ought to be made for the mynister. Very necessary to be learned of all Christians. By Eusebius Paget.</title>
                  <title>Godlie and fruitefull sermon, made upon the 20. &amp; 21. verses of the 14. chapter of the booke of Genesis.</title>
                  <author>Pagit, Eusebius, 1547?-1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Iohn Wolfe, for Thomas Man, dwelling in Paternoster rowe, at the signe of the Talbot,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1583.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A fruitefull and godly sermon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Pages marked.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6118:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6118:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A GODLIE <hi>AND FRVITEFVLL</hi> Sermon, made vpon the 20. <hi>&amp;</hi> 21. <hi>verſes of the</hi> 14. <hi>Chapter <hi>of the booke of Geneſis: Wherein there</hi>
               </hi> is taught, what prouiſion ought to be made for the myniſter.</p>
            <p>Very neceſſary to be learned of all Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Euſebius Paget</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <head>VBIQVE FLORET.</head>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON <hi>Imprinted by <hi>Iohn Wolfe,</hi> for</hi> Thomas Man, <hi>dwelling in</hi> Paternoſter rowe, at the ſigne of the Talbot, 1583.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:6118:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6118:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Geneſis. <hi>14.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>20</hi>
                     </bibl> Abram gaue him Tythe of all.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>21</hi>
                     </bibl> Then the King of Sodome ſayde to Abram. Giue me the perſonnes, take the goods to thyſelfe.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE laſt time beloued that I was in this place, which was the fourth day of this laſt weeke, you heard that this thirde and laſte parte of this chapter,<note place="margin">The repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</note> contayneth the tryumph of <hi>Abram</hi> after the victory: In whoſe returne from the battel he was met of <hi>2.</hi> Kinges, the one King of <hi>Sodome,</hi> the other was the King of <hi>Salem.</hi> Wherein we conſidered firſt, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> dealings of <hi>Abram</hi> &amp; the king of <hi>Sodome</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt part: ſecondly, the dealings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>Abram</hi> and <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> in the ſecond part. In the firſt part whereas <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the King of <hi>Sodome</hi> came forth to meete <hi>Abram:</hi> We did note, that aduerſity tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth many good leſſons, which men in proſperitie will neuer learne: namelye, the King of <hi>Sodome</hi> who before this time wold neither pitie <hi>Abram</hi> being a ſtranger, nor reuerence him for his reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb facs="tcp:6118:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
which hee profeſſed euerye where, and ſet vp badges and Enſignes of the ſame in euery place where hee came, but in his proſperity had his whole delight in wantonneſſe and pride, and is nowe by aduerſſite taught humilitie: and hee commeth forth to meete and ſalute <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bram.</hi> Secondly, that this king now ſaw what profite he got by pride, and what the waye of wickedneſſe had brought him vnto, and that the eſtate of <hi>Abram,</hi> howe troubleſome, mad, and fooliſh ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it ſeemed to him, yet to be farre bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more glorious then his, ſoe, there is not ſo wicked a man but that he once acknowledgeth his owne eſtate to bee miſerable, and the eſtate of Gods chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to be moſt happye and bleſſed. Next the hiſtorie of <hi>Melchizedech</hi> followed, inſerted as in a parentheſis, Wherein wee conſidered. Firſt what he was, <hi>2.</hi> what he did, <hi>3.</hi> what he ſayde. Out of the firſt part, which is at large deſcribed in the ſeuenth to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> we conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red firſt his name, to wit <hi>Melchizedech,</hi> which ſignifieth righteouſnes, and that he was king of <hi>Salem,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is peace, wherin
<pb facs="tcp:6118:3"/>
the holye ghoſt noteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> righteouſnes is king of peace. &amp; that righteouſnes gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in the kingdome of peace, &amp; no peace where vnrighteouſnes raigneth, as the prophet <hi>Iſa. <hi>57.21.</hi>
               </hi> ſaith, ther is no peace ſaith my God to the wicked. Secondlye, in that firſt part wee noted that he was without Father and Mother. For that the holy Ghoſt doth make no mention of them. Wherein I ſhewed how vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they deale, that would haue him to bee eyther <hi>Shem,</hi> or an Angell, or the ſonne of God, and brought foorth reaſons to confute thoſe fancies. Thirdly, wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered that hee was King and Prieſte, noting in all theſe things that he was a figure of Chriſt. Firſt in his name, for that Chriſt is righteouſneſſe it ſelfe, raigning in mens conſcyences, &amp; bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing peace to the ſoule: ſecondly in his parents Chriſt is without father in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his manhood, &amp; without mother in reſpect of his godhead: Thirdly in his offices, Chriſt is a King to raigne, and a prieſte to offer vp ſacrifice to God his father for euer. Then we conſidered the deedes of <hi>Melchizedech,</hi> which was the
<pb facs="tcp:6118:4"/>
bringing forth of bread and wine to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue the wearied army of <hi>Abram:</hi> where in I confuted the fancy of the Papiſtes, that would haue this bread and wine of <hi>Melchizedech,</hi> to be a fygure of theyr Maſſe: Firſt, ſhewing that if there had beene anye ſuch matter in it, the holye Ghoſt woulde haue noted it in the <hi>7.</hi> to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> where he deſcrybeth him ſo largely. For if it had figured ſo greate a myſtery as they account their maſſe to bee, the holy Ghoſt woulde not haue ſet ſo light by it, as to haue ſayde neuer a word of it. <hi>Melchizedech</hi> brought foorth bread, but they deny their ſacrifice to bee bread, but the body of chriſt: In denying their wafar cake to be bread, they ſaye truely, for it is a paltry thing, not mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the ſenſes of the receauers to that conſideration it ſhould: Beſides that, it hath beene made as many wright, of bad confections, as dogs greaſe. And ſome of their aunceſtors before tyme made their ſtuffe with infants blood, and ſome with more filthy &amp; abhominable things then are here to be named. <hi>Melchize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dech</hi> brought forth bread and wine to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh
<pb facs="tcp:6118:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the feeble ſouldiars, wherein was noted, that the Lorde doth alwaies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for thoſe that trauaile in his buſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and take paines to deliuer the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, as <hi>Abram</hi> aduenturing to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his brother <hi>Lot,</hi> receiueth comfort by a ſtranger. <hi>Melchizedech</hi> bleſſed <hi>Abram</hi> from the lord, in which his words were noted, that bleſſings came from God, &amp; that they are the Lordes bleſſings, and not mans that ſtande, and his curſes that take effect. Next they that comfort the afflicted are bleſſed of God, and they that greeue the Spyrite of GOD in his children, by adding afflictions to afflictions, are curſed of God: commyng from that to the title wherein he called him poſſeſſour of Heauen, and Earth. I noted he gaue God theſe titles, beeing onely poſſeſſour of Heauen, and that the Pope can not open and ſhut it with his pardons at his pleaſure, for heauen is the Lordes: and next in that he nameth him poſſeſſour of earth: I noted that he will take account of vs whether wee vſe it as he hath directed vs, or abuſe it contrary to his will, and therein we ſee
<pb facs="tcp:6118:5"/>
what a happye and bleſſed thing it is for Gods children, whoſe kingdome and inheritance is not vpon the earth but in heauen, where no tyrannous oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours can trouble and annoy: on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide what a wofull chaunge ſhall theſe oppreſſing tyrants make, which ſay, now y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth is theirs to ſerue their luſts, and then they muſt anſwere to the profeſſor of it, and muſt flit to hell from the earth for their abuſing it. So <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizedech</hi> ended his ſpeech with thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing and yeelding the glorye of that triumph vnto God for the victorye as to him was due, and theſe were the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall notes which I gaue then as I remember. Now it reſteth before wee enter into the hiſtorie of the king of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> that we conſider what <hi>Abram</hi> did to <hi>Melchizedech:</hi> The holy Ghoſt ſaith, <hi>Abram</hi> gaue him Tyth of all, wherein he giueth vs to conſider that <hi>Abram</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing lightened by Gods ſpirite, ſawe in <hi>Melchizedech</hi> ſome more excellent thing then is ordinarilye found in men, and therefore he gaue him an extraordinarye entertainment, and preſented him with ſuch a preſent, as we reade not of in the
<pb facs="tcp:6118:5"/>
Scriptures, vntill we come to this place therefore that we may the better vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it, let vs obſerue. Firſt, what it is that is giuen, namely Tythes. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to whom it was giuen, to <hi>Melchize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dech.</hi> Thirdly by whome they were gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, by <hi>Abram,</hi> and Fourthly, whereof theſe Tythes were, which are ſet down by the holye Ghoſt in the epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes <hi>7.</hi>
               </hi> to be of the ſpoyles which <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bram</hi> had gotten in the Warres, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fourth verſe. Tythes were a portion which the Lorde reſerued to him ſelfe to be paide to himſelfe, by them to whome he gaue the poſſeſſion of the earth, and the enioying of Earthlye bleſſings, ſo <hi>Moiſes</hi> ſaith <hi>Leuit. <hi>27.30.</hi> The tith is the Lords, it is holy to the Lord.</hi> So <hi>Iacob</hi> ſaid, <hi>Gene. <hi>28.22.</hi> Of all thou ſhalt giue me, I will giue the tenth to thee,</hi> which thing was yeelded as a teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of their gratefull &amp; thankefull minds to him that beſtowed thoſe benefites vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them, and as an acknowledgement that all they had was the Lordes, and they held the ſame of him in chiefe. For the ſecond part to whom it was giuen,
<pb facs="tcp:6118:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
it is here noted that it was to <hi>Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zedech,</hi> an axcellent perſon, a figure of Chriſt, the ſonne of God, a choyce man placed by the Lord, as it were in his own roome, to take homage of <hi>Abram</hi> for the Lords right, and thus the Lord hath delt in ſundry places of the ſcripture, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing diuers ſonnes of men to bee his deputies, to receaue reliefe of thoſe outward ſignes of the inwarde honour due vnto him ſelfe, of which ſortes there bee principally foure. Firſt, the <hi>Leuites</hi> appointed to teach Gods people, who being firſt curſed by <hi>Iacob</hi> for the bloodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the handes of <hi>Leui,</hi> and left wyth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out any tribe or inheritance, but to bee deuided in <hi>Iacob,</hi> and ſcattered in <hi>Iſraell. Gen. 49.7.</hi> their handes were after ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified of the Lord for ſhewing their loue &amp; zeale to the Lord, in killing the idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which had worſhipped y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> calfe. The curſe of deuiding &amp; ſcattering, the Lorde applied as a meanes that his law might be taught in euery corner of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> and the loſſe of their inheritance hee recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed by feeding them wyth his owne portion, and promiſing them that hee
<pb facs="tcp:6118:6"/>
himſelfe would be their lot and their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance. <hi>Nomb. 18.20.</hi> The ſecond ſort are the poore, the ſtraunger, the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and the widow. <hi>Deut. 26.12.</hi> The third ſort are kings, whome the Lorde hath placed in his owne roome, to guide and gouerne his people, as <hi>Samuell</hi> ſayde when the people would needes haue a King, he will take the tenth of your ſede and of your fieldes and giue it to his <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuches</hi> and to his ſeruants. <hi>1. Sam. 8.15.</hi> The fourth ſort, were the children of the Prophetes trayned vp at ſchoole at <hi>Rama,</hi> and ſuch other places as Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, that they might be the apter for the matters of the Lord, as may bee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered by ſundry places of the ſcripture. Next commeth to be conſidered, who payd Tythes: namely <hi>Abram:</hi> wherin the author to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> noteth what an excellent man <hi>Melchizedech</hi> was, to whom <hi>Abram</hi> the <hi>Patriark</hi> paid tithes: but farre more excellent is the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Prieſthood of Chriſt, figured by <hi>Melchizedech:</hi> he alſo doth teach vs that the end and aboliſhing of the prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode of <hi>Leui</hi> was figured in this, that
<pb facs="tcp:6118:7"/>
               <hi>Leui</hi> in the loines of <hi>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> paid Tithes to <hi>Melchizedech.</hi> This alſo was figured in that the prieſtes, &amp; <hi>Leuites</hi> paid tithes (of thoſe Tythes which were brought them) to the high prieſt (who was alſo a figure of Chriſt) <hi>Num. <hi>18.26.</hi>
               </hi> Laſtly in this text we are to note whereof he payd tythes, which the holy Ghoſt to the <hi>Heb. <hi>7.4.</hi>
               </hi> anſwereth to be of the ſpoyles gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by his handes. There were ſundrie ſorts of Tythes payed, as of the fruites of the ground, of the gaines of their handes, &amp; of the encreaſe of their Cattel, whereby we ſee the great care that God had for the <hi>Leuites</hi> in prouiding, for them that had no inheritance of their owne: ſo that as the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had encreaſe of any fruites, the <hi>Leuites</hi> attending vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on religion, had their portion of the ſame. As theſe tithes were of diuers ſorts, ſo were they diuerſly paid, of ſome they paide the firſt fruites, of ſome the third, of ſome the tenth: ſome were paid in mony, &amp; ſome otherwiſe, whereby we ſee that the holy ghoſt ſpeaking of tythes is not alwaies to be vnderſtod of tenths ſome do take it, but theſe Tythes were
<pb facs="tcp:6118:7"/>
of the fruits gotten by <hi>Abram</hi> his hands. Thus haue you heard the ſumme of this text. But now it is conuenient (this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt time that we finde the mat-of Tythes, ſpoken of ſince wee began this booke of <hi>Geneſis</hi>) that we ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deeper into theſe wordes and learne ſomewhat out of them for our ſelues. Which matter I would gladly paſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer for the auoyding of falſe ſurmiſes &amp; ſiniſter reports, but that our Sauiour in that commiſſion giuen in the latter end of the <hi>28.</hi> after <hi>Mathew,</hi> giueth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, ſaying: <hi>Teach them to doe al that I haue commanded you:</hi> And the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in the <hi>Act. 20. cap. <hi>26.</hi>
               </hi> &amp; <hi>27. <hi>verſes</hi>
               </hi> proteſteth that he is free from the bloude of all men, for that he kept no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing backe, but had ſhewed them al the counſel of God: the miniſter therefore muſt teach al that Chriſt hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, euen all the councels of God reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in his word, and hee that keepeth them backe, ſhall be found guiltie both of the breach of the commandement of Chriſt, and alſo of the bloud of his flocke. The Paſtor muſt teach three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb facs="tcp:6118:8"/>
and you muſt learne not onelye to know the duetie of a Miniſter to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but alſo of the people towardes their miniſter. Howſoeuer therefore the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine deliuered, ſhall be miſtaken or wreſted, yet the truth muſt bee deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, let men take it as they wyll, the Lord will giue it ſuch ſucceſſe as he ſhall thinke beſt. Some peraduenture will aſke what this matter of tythes apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth to the miniſterie now? and will (to ſaue their goods) ſay, that theſe were ceremoniall lawes, and ſo were abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Chriſtes comming. To whome I anſwere, that the Lorde (of that portion reſerued vnto him ſelfe) appointed ſome part to the <hi>Leuites</hi> for the mayntenance of the miniſtery about the Lords worke. and ſome part of them for the ſacryfices of meate offeringes, drinke offeringes, ſinne offeringes, treſpaſſe offerings, and peace offeringes: this laſt part for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices was ceremoniall, and ſo Chriſte the body being come, the ſhadowes are ended. But this, that homage bee done to the King of all Kinges, and that the mynyſtrye be maintained for the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="tcp:6118:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
forth of the true worſhip of GOD, and ſuppreſſing of all falſe worſhips, is not ceremoniall but morall, and ſhall ſo long continue as any face of a Church or religion ſhall be vpon the earth. Hee therefore that ſhall ſay that this is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither ceremoniall and ended by Chriſt, ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſt is a hinderer, and leſſe care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for the miniſtry of the Goſpell, then he was for the exerciſe of figures &amp; ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows vnder the law. But many of theſe men which ſo willinglye woulde haue this lawe for the maintenance of the miniſtrie to be diſanulled as ceremony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and yet do like inough, &amp; to much of other ceremonies, not onelye Iewiſhe, but Antichriſtian and Popiſh, euen ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the heathen, do hereby declare that it is not the ceremony, which they would haue buried, but the preaching of the Goſpell that they can not abide, for that it rippeth vp their conſcience, it rubbeth iuſt where they are galled, and diſcouereth their ſinnes: It is not a ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonye, it is this that greeueth them. On the other ſide, ſatan (ſeeking to bring the miniſters either to ſlacke their dily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence
<pb facs="tcp:6118:9"/>
in Gods matters, and to get their bread by other meanes, or by pouertie to runne into debt, contempt and ſhame) haith raiſed vp a ſort of couetous men, which pul from the miniſters what they can, and will as willingly haue their guts drawne out of their belly, as they wil part from any of their goodes for the maintenance of the miniſters. And theſe men will ſeeme to haue ſcripture for their purpoſe, yea they haue this at their fingers end out of <hi>Mat. 10.<hi>8.</hi> Freely ye haue receyued, freely giue,</hi> ſo far they haue learned, but no further, for that it ſerued not their purpoſe: For our Sauiour left not his Apoſtles without their prouiſion in this their painefull iourney, but in the ſame chapter ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in euery citie where they ſhould come, that they ſhould be receyued into the houſes of them that were worthie. and that prouiſion ſhould be ſet before them for their maintenance, but if they found not places fit for that peace they brought, they ſhould ſhake the duſt from their feete to bee a witneſſe of greater vengeance to that place, then that which
<pb facs="tcp:6118:9"/>
light vpon <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrhe:</hi> But few are thoſe houſes that ſuch men holde and keepe, where the miniſter may be receiued with his wife and children, &amp; haue main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance ſet before them with ioy: yea fewe they are in deede where the ſincere mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter may eate his meate with ioy, but that the aboundance of ſinne ſhall make him thinke his breade to be as grauel betwene his teeth, and his drinke to bee as worme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood to his taſte, and ſo with greefe they would ſoon make the miniſter with ſhame to go &amp; begge his breade. But as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour that gaue that former particuler charge, to giue freely, and to take neither bag nor ſcrip nor money, ſo afterwards in the <hi>22.</hi> of <hi>Luke <hi>35.</hi>
               </hi> he doth aſke his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles whether they wanted any thing or no, when he thus ſent them forth and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded therewithall, <hi>now he that hath a ſcrippe, let him poſſeſſe it, and he that hath not a ſword let him ſell his coate and buye one,</hi> that is, the world will growe to ſuch miſery, and the miniſtery to ſuch afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery one will be readie to ſcratch &amp; pul from you. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vſe ye the meanes that are lawfull in the feare of the lord for your maintenance.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6118:10"/>That this matter may bee the playner layde open, and made more manifeſt to the capacitie of our vnderſtanding. Let vs con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſider, firſt whether there be any ſtipend ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poynted for the miniſtry or no? <hi>2.</hi> How the ſame ſhould be paid? <hi>3.</hi> to whom it ſhould be paid? For the firſt, the law of nature taught it them that had not the law of God to direct them, ſundry godly kinges haue executed it, the Fathers directed by Gods ſpirit before the law was written vſed it, God by his law eſtabliſhed it, Chriſt hath ratified it vnto vs in the new teſtament, and the Apoſtles haue in ſundrie places taught it, &amp; becauſe the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> made a large diſcourſe of this matter, and vſed ſundrie reaſons to proue the ſame, let vs leaue all other, and rippe vp thoſe in the <hi>1. <hi>Cor. 9.</hi>
               </hi> where he vſeth foure principal rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to confirme the ſame. The firſt gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the example of the Apoſtles, The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond by compariſon. The third of the law writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the fourth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> authority of Chriſt. Firſt he ſaith it is lawfull, yea the other A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles haue power to take maintenance of you for them and their wiues, and may not I and <hi>Barnabas</hi> haue it? His reaſon of
<pb facs="tcp:6118:10"/>
compariſon he followeth thus. The ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er hath his coſtes borne in his warfare, the huſbandman eateth of the fruits of his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, the ſhepeheard feedeth of the milke of his flocke. The Oxe hath his mouth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to feed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> corne he treadeth out. They that wayted of the altar were fed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, we the miniſters are the ſoldiers and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne bearers in your chriſtian wars, we are Gods huſbandmen, you are Gods huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandrie, we are the ſhepheardes, you are the ſheepe, we treade you out &amp; deuide vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you the breade of life, the word of God, we miniſter not vnto you figures and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes as the <hi>Leuits</hi> did, but the goſpel, the power of God to ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, why ſhould not we then be maintayned as ſoldiers? why reape we not of our labours as huſband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men? why are we not fed as ſhepheards? Why haue we not the libertie of Oxen? Why liue we not of our calling as the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uits</hi> did? Is our calling more vile then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other occupation? Are not our labours worthie meat and drinke? Yes, yes, your gaine is great by exchaunge with vs, for droſſe you haue golde, for carnall thinges, ſpiritual. And for earthly things, heauenly.
<pb facs="tcp:6118:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Yea further, you can finde nothing in the world to be laid in equal balla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to weigh againſt the worde of God: from reaſoning thus by compariſon, he procéedeth to his ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gument of authoritie of the law written, &amp; therein he ſtandeth not long, for he ſaid it is ſufficient, his word is a reaſon of force, and his will is a perfect rule of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Then he goeth forward to his <hi>4.</hi> argu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, and proueth that Chriſt alowed &amp; ratified the ſame in the goſpel, ordeyning that they which preach the goſpell ſhould liue of the goſpell. And the Apoſtle to the <hi>Gal. 6.6.7.</hi> vſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame reaſon vſed before in the law, for there the Lord challenged it as a law due vnto himſelfe, &amp; here he ſaith, <hi>that he which defraudeth the miniſter, decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth himſelfe, &amp; mocketh God:</hi> for as he was king before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law, &amp; in the law before the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of Chriſt in the fleſh, ſo is he king ſtil, the preaching of the goſpel is the ſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his kingdome, the miniſters are his ſcepter bearers, &amp; therefore he ſheweth by the Apoſtle. <hi>1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17.</hi> that they which labour in the word &amp; doctrine, are worthie of double honour, that is, a liberall allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the maintenance of him and his.
<pb facs="tcp:6118:11"/>
For the ſecond part, how the ſame ſhoulde be paide, or whereof raiſed, the holy Ghoſt hath not appoynted, therfore to ſay that the tenthes belong to the miniſters as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Lord, we haue no warrant for it, neyther dare I ſay that the magiſtrate may not appoynt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tenthes for the maine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the miniſtrie, except I ſaw the ſame forbidden by the lord. As kings haue receyued their kingdomes &amp; ſcepters from the Lord, ſo muſt they endeuour that the kingdome of God may haue place in their dominions, that he may rule amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by his worde, &amp; that the miniſters be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently prouided for, as they will anſwere for it to the king of kings, of whome they holde their crownes in chiefe: but it is left at libertie to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to raiſe it, either by tenths of fruits of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, or of cattel, or of mony, or by what means they ſhal in their godly wiſedome thinke moſt conuenient, &amp; the more certaine they make this portion, the mo miſchiefes they do preuent, for the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of it vncertaine, doth often cauſe the miniſter, eyther to make merchandize of the worde, or for gaine to flatter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> welthy, or with ſhame for want to beg, or for néed
<pb facs="tcp:6118:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to ſtarue, all which ſubtil practiſes Satan dayly putteth in execution, ſéeking thereby either to ouerthrow the miniſtrie, or to make it by ſuch blemiſhes to looſe the force and bewtie of the ſame. But though ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates ſhould be careleſſe in theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, yet the people of God muſt be careful to do their duetie in this reſpect. There was no king of <hi>Canaan</hi> that be law co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Abram</hi> to pay theſe tithes, neither was there any Chriſtian prince in the prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church, that by law appointed main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance for the miniſters, yet <hi>Abram</hi> paid, &amp; the Apoſtles &amp; biſhops after them were prouided for. But to come nerer to ſée how they muſt be paid. This muſt be paid reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly, readily and liberally: religiouſly as to God for the enlarging of his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the defence of the trueth, and mainte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his true worſhip. It muſt be done readily in time conuenient, &amp; of a willing minde. It muſt be done liberally, that the miniſter be not driuen to ſlack his calling and to employ his time in other thinges, thereby to get his liuing: by this liberalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie I mean not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhould be glutted vp with dainties &amp; maintayned pompouſly,
<pb facs="tcp:6118:12"/>
for that is as great a miſchiefe on the other ſide. For when Satan can not ſtop y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the goſpel by pennury &amp; ſcarcitie, then he tryeth to choake &amp; ſmother it with the glory of the world, and this way alas he doth too much preuaile. But thogh there be ſome either made ſlow of ſpeach, or alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether tong-tied by this God <hi>Mammon</hi> &amp; ſo bewitched, that they can like better of miniſters that liue as <hi>Athieſts,</hi> drunkerds, wantons &amp; old doting prieſtes, then they do of paineful &amp; ſincere preachers, yet it is a wonder to ſée with what curſing &amp; ſwea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring, how ſlackly &amp; ſlowly, &amp; with what pinching and ſparing the reſt haue their portions, vnleſſe they had all conſpired to ouerthrowe the miniſtry. <hi>Abram</hi> was riche &amp; yet paid tithes: the rich now a daies that ſhould giue moſt liberally, wil for the moſt part take tithes, there are verie few of them that will pay any. The miniſters are driuen to liue of that they can haue of the pooreſt, which are oft times ſo ſcraped, that they are more meete to take almeſſe then to pay tithes. In the booke of <hi>Nehem. <hi>13.4.</hi>
               </hi> there is a ſtory recorded how <hi>Tobiah</hi> the <hi>Ammonite</hi> kinſman to <hi>Eliaſhib</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſt
<pb facs="tcp:6118:13"/>
had gotten by his fauour into the chamber made for the prouiſion of the houſe of God and of the <hi>Leuites,</hi> ſo that they fled to their land, &amp; left the houſe of God voyd, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Nehemiah</hi> heard of it, he obtayned libertie of king <hi>Artahſhaſht,</hi> &amp; came to <hi>Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> with griefe, he found the ſame to be true, he caſt out all <hi>Tobiah</hi> his ſtuffe, and reſorted thoſe things to their former vſe. If that our no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble prince wold now ſend forth ſome god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; zealous <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> to looke to theſe matters now, he might find a nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biahs</hi> entred into the chambers, appointed for the prouiſion of the miniſtrie. Firſt hee ſhould find y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Abbeys (kinſmen to the high prieſt of <hi>Rome</hi>) began to make this ſpoyle, &amp; got into their hands the beſt bene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fices by impropriating them, they are ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne, theſe ſpoiles are not reſtored, but many men liue of that they ſtole from the miniſtry. Secondly he ſhould find a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of biſhops equal in this ſinne, with <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaſhih,</hi> or with that high prieſt of <hi>Rome,</hi> for they haue ſpoyled many benefices by confirming leaſes to their kinſmen by power, or by bloude, or by the purſe, yea I know one biſhop in this realme, that hath
<pb facs="tcp:6118:13"/>
confirmed I thinke nere <hi>20.</hi> of the beſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices in his dioceſſe, ſome to his children, ſome to his kinſmen, ſome to his officers, ſome for mony to diuers that are as badde as <hi>Ammonites</hi> in religion, Thirdly he ſhal finde a number of patrones that will bee ſo nigh kinſmen to the miniſters, that they will haue all the houſe and profits, &amp; alowe them ſcraps with the ſeruing men, when they haue wayted on their patrones tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, or they will coſin them of the houſe and gleabe, it is parte of their inheritance, it ſtandeth as conueniently for them, as <hi>Nabothes</hi> vyneyard did for <hi>Ahab,</hi> let our coſins the pield prieſtes dwell in ſome bad cotages, theſe houſes are meeter for gentle men: or they will for coſinage haue the tith corne for prouiſion for their houſe, &amp; leaue their poore coſin tithe gooſe and tith calfe, with the egges at Eaſter, at leaſt they will haue their owne tithes. Neuer a chaplaine of them all ſhall put them beſides it. Some what there muſt be giuen to the myſtreſſe their wiues, or to finde a childe at Schoole. Fourthly, he ſhall finde many wealthy and mightie men to be ſo neere kinſmen to the miniſters, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they will pay either nothing,
<pb facs="tcp:6118:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
or very litle, they will pleaſure them ſome other way. But if they may not haue it as they liſt, they will bee neither their coſins nor friends, the preacher nor goſpeller muſt not harbour there, he were better to be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a mile fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them. To be ſhort, I am not able to recken vp the practiſes that thys good commiſſioner ſhoulde find deuiſed by ſatan and put in execution by men, for the coſining &amp; ſpoyle of the miniſtry, prophane me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue delt better with their idle prieſtes then we with our miniſters. <hi>Pharao</hi> that heatheniſhe king, in whom was no religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, toke this order when the great famine was in <hi>Egipt,</hi> as appeareth in <hi>Gen. <hi>47.22</hi>
               </hi> that his idoll prieſtes were maintained of his own charge. <hi>Iezabel</hi> that Qeeene ſo full of wickednes, mayntained <hi>Baals</hi> prieſtes at her owne table <hi>1. <hi>King.</hi> 18.17.</hi> &amp; <hi>Michah</hi> as it is in the booke of <hi>Iudges <hi>17.5.10.</hi>
               </hi> made him an Idole, got him a prieſte, and prouided for him his handfull, to wit, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry liberally: equall with <hi>Pharao,</hi> with <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Zabell,</hi> and with <hi>Michah,</hi> were our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runners in the time of popery, who cram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med both the bellies &amp; the purſſes of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans hirelings, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chapplaines of <hi>Antichriſt</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:6118:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
who coulde do nothinge but ſay a Maſſe or mumble vp a mattins, but nowe in the time of the Goſpell to get any thing for the maintenance of the miniſtery of the ſame, is as I ſaid before, as greeuous to them as the pulling of their bowels out of their bellies, yea, they ſeeke to put awaye euen that which is leſſe. Here I might take oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to ſhew both how religion &amp; iuſtice, godlines and honeſty are made ſhipwrack of by the ſpoile of the miniſtery: for thereby eight commandements of the ten are bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. For neither the knowledge of God, nor the true eſtimation and loue of him commanded in the firſt commandement: nor the auoiding of Idolatrye, and ſetting forth of the true worſhip of God, preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in the ſecond commandement, nor the reuerence of the name of God ſet foorth in the thirde, nor the obſeruation of the ſabboth, eſtabliſhed in the <hi>4.</hi> Nor the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the miniſtery appointed in the fift. Nor the auoiding of bloudguiltines &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeruation of life giuen in charge in the <hi>6.</hi> Nor the giuing to euery man his right re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in the <hi>8.</hi> Nor the hauing of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented hart without any motion, coueting
<pb facs="tcp:6118:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
or deſiring y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is another mans, ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly exacted of vs in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tenth, are any whit at all regarded, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by violating all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements in the firſt table, it ſheweth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there wanteth godlines in him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpoileth the miniſtery: &amp; by breaking <hi>4.</hi> commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of the ſecond table, it declareth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honeſty hath ſuffred a very da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack: At a word it giueth an euideth te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there remaineth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſmall remnant, either of religion, or elſe of righteouſnes. Now we are to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe tithes, ſtipends, or maintenance (cal the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as you pleaſe) are to be paid. They are to be paid to ſuch as are enſigne berers in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords wars: they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> preach the goſpell muſt liue of the goſpell. <hi>Abram</hi> paid tithes to <hi>Melchizedech,</hi> who had applied him ſelfe to comfort <hi>Abram,</hi> to giue thankes to God to preach &amp; ſhewe forth the praiſes of God. Our ſauiour commands y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the hier ſhoulde be paide to the labourers, &amp; the Apoſtle ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointeth the double honor to them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> trauel in the word &amp; doctrine, and he commandeth <hi>2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.10.</hi> that if there were any which would not work y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhould not eat, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the maſſe men, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> idle ſhepheards, the dumb
<pb facs="tcp:6118:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
dogs, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blind &amp; ſleepy watchmen, the wine prophets, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fooliſh ignorant ſhepheards, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> idle loiterers, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſlowbellies, haue no part of this allowance allotted vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, either by the law, the prophets, our ſauiour, or his Apoſtles, their allowance is woe, the pryce of blood for the guiltines of the people of god Yet theſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preach leaſt, fleece moſt, and if they procure a quarter ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, this muſt be one principall caueat to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preacher, the people are ſlacke in paying their tithes, they muſt be ſtirred vp to féede the idle flatterer, and ſome preachers are ſo ſimple as to ſerue the greedy chapleins hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor for his Noble. Lorde in thy good time remooue theſe loiterers, ſcraping ſléecers, &amp; time ſeruers, and place in their roome ſuch painfull labourers as wil bear the weight of the burdens, and abide y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> brunt and heat of the day, &amp; be eſtemed worthy to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> honor y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt appointed for them. Now it reſteth that we proceede with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hiſtory of the king of <hi>Sodome,</hi> wherin is ſet down, firſt the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication which the king of <hi>Sodome</hi> made to <hi>Abram</hi> expreſſed in the <hi>21.</hi> ver. next the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere of <hi>Abram</hi> to the ſame, which folow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth in the <hi>3.</hi> laſt verſes. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king of <hi>Sodoms</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:6118:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſupplication. <hi>Giue me the perſons, take the goods to thy ſelfe:</hi> is ſhewed great equitye &amp; charitye, equity towards <hi>Abram,</hi> in that he would take neither men nor mony with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Abrams</hi> leaue, for that by his painefull trauels, &amp; endangering his own life, he had gotten them as ſpoiles in the wars, &amp; cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the men he deſireth not the goods, but is willing to leaue them with him: on the other ſide, he ſheweth great charity &amp; pitye fowardes his ſubiects, in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſueth ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſet at liberty. This ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is a notable ſupplication, and a very rare example of a ſingular ſute. If we conſider all circumſtances. Firſt he is very poore, then his countreye is ſpoiled, next his goods are caried away, he is left very bare, why doth he not rather in reſpect of him ſelfe, ſeeke the riches and aſke the goods, then craue the men. Why doth he not conſider y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath nothing to keepe them on, no not for himſelfe. All theſe conſiderations are ſwallowed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue he beareth to his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, his mercy to his men ful of miſeries &amp; calamities, cauſeth him to regard none of thoſe things, but he ſaith, <hi>Giue me the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, take the goods to thy ſelfe.</hi> This exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb facs="tcp:6118:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
is ſeldome folowed (to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhame I ſpeak it of the miſerable worldlings that liue in theſe daies) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this prophane king not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing God, dwelling at the vile place <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> ſhewed more mercy towards men, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many called chriſtians, dwelling in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of Chriſtian realmes, do to their Chriſtian brethren. Few are thoſe maiſters y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tender not their beaſts more then their ſeruants, few are the Landlords that regard not the goods more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men, as the oppreſſing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore, by rackinges of rentes, by exceſſiue fines, by extraordinary payments, gnaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them the bread gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with paineful hands, before it can come into the childrens bellies, and the vnharbouring of the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourleſſe, when they haue ſcraped them to the bones doth witneſſe, and the cry of the ſame doth come to the eares of the Lord of hoſts, by the pitiful co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaints of men, wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and children, widowes, &amp; Orphans, yea, the fatherleſſe infants, are driuen to waile, becauſe that mercileſſe Landlordes craue the goods &amp; haue no compaſſion vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon chriſtians. To be ſhort, few are thoſe miniſters y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> care more for the ſoules, then for the ſtipends &amp; tithes, as the couetous
<pb facs="tcp:6118:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
heaping vp of many benefices togeather the number of none reſidentes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> careleſſe ſetting ouer of ſoules, to iourney men and hirelings that will ſerue beſt chepe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſcraping for tithes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeldome preaching yea many great <hi>Rabbyns</hi> which would be counted ioly preachers, will preach no of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tener then ſhame, law, or iniunction com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Yea ſome that ſhould ſpur others forward, may be preſented in their ſeuerall charges for defaulte of their quarter Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. This teſtifieth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſeeke not the ſoules but the goods. Thus in theſe fewe wordes we ſee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> courſe of the world in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, which is to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned by this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the king of <hi>Sodom,</hi> &amp; I feare it wil not be amended til God conſume vs &amp; our corruptions with fire, as he did the <hi>Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits.</hi> The time is paſt, the anſwere of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bram</hi> I defer to the <hi>4.</hi> day of this weke. Let vs pray that we may profit by that wee haue now heard.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:6118:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
